"How to Suppress Your Appetite
and Naturally Boost GLP-1"
About 20 years ago,
there was a discovery
that would forever change
our ideas about fiber:
Our gut bacteria eat
the fiber we eat
to produce important
signaling compounds
called short-chain fatty acids.
But before I get carried away,
a little science lesson
to frame the discovery.
Cells are the fundamental unit
of life.
We’re composed
of trillions of them.
They communicate with each other
through receptors
on the surface of our cells.
That’s how many hormones work;
it’s like a lock and key.
Hormones are
signaling messengers,
each with a unique shape.
When released
into the bloodstream,
they circulate
through the body
until they find a receptor
they can fit into.
Once the key is in the lock,
it can turn on or off
a whole series of reactions
in the target cell.
The largest family
of cell receptors
is known as G protein-coupled
receptors (GPCRs, for short).
More than a third of the drugs
currently on the market
work by plugging
into these receptors.
That’s how drugs
like antihistamines work.
We’ve discovered hundreds
of different GPCRs,
but, remarkably, we don’t yet
know what many of them do.
We have the lock; we just
don’t know what key fits.
Accordingly, they’re called
"orphan" receptors.
Two of these mystery receptors,
known only as GPR43 and GPR41,
were found heavily expressed
throughout the body
in our immune and fat cells,
and in our gut, muscles,
and heart.
We knew they must be vital,
but we didn’t know what
activated them until 2003,
when they were "deorphanized"
(that’s actually
what scientists call it).
The keys that fit
into those important locks
were the short-chain fatty acids
that our gut bacteria make
when we feed them fiber.
This is how our gut bacteria
may communicate with us.
Renamed
free fatty acid receptors,
their existence is now
considered crucial insight
into how fiber could play
such an important role
in so many
of our chronic diseases.
Hormones are defined
as signaling messengers
produced in one organ
that circulate
through the bloodstream
and have a regulatory effect
on another organ.
So, these
short-chain fatty acids
can be considered hormones.
It’s just that the organ that
produces them is our microbiome,
the bacteria
that populate our gut.
They can’t make these hormones,
though, without fiber.
What do the free fatty acid
receptors on our fat cells do?
Remember leptin, the hormone
produced by fat cells
that helps tell our brain
how to regulate our body weight?
Short-chain fatty acids
stimulate the production
of leptin.
This can be demonstrated
in a petri dish
with individual fat cells,
or by using fat tissue samples
removed during surgery.
Drip on some
short-chain fatty acids
and leptin production
almost doubles.
Leptin is
an "anorectic" hormone,
so-called because it generates
a loss of appetite and weight,
but it does so
over the long term.
Leptin levels slowly rise
as the volume of body fat
gradually increases.
There are other
anorectic hormones
that instead work rapidly,
signaling our brain
on more of a meal-to-meal basis.
Two of these short-term appetite
suppressants are PYY and GLP-1,
which are both secreted
by specialized L cells
that line our colon.
Guess what receptors are crowded
all over their surface?
Free fatty acid receptors.
Drip some short-chain
fatty acids onto L cells
and they start churning out
PYY and GLP-1.
You can do this in a petri dish
or in a person,
either by infusing their rectums
with a short-chain
fatty acid enema
or the old-fashioned way,
by feeding people fiber,
or even better,
fiber-rich foods,
like this whole rye kernel
wheat bread.
These hormones then get released
into the bloodstream,
where they can shoot up into
the appetite center of our brain
and turn down our cravings.
The flipside is ghrelin,
the so-called hunger hormone.
Ghrelin levels rise in our blood
before a meal
to stimulate our appetite,
and fall down again once we eat,
before slowly building back up
to drive us back to the kitchen.
But four hours after eating
just 24 grams of fiber,
people’s ghrelin levels
are suppressed as much
as if they had just had
500 calories’ worth of food.
Longer studies show
similar effects.
11- and 12-year-old children
with overweight or obesity
who were randomized to increased
fiber intake for 16 weeks
ended up eating
hundreds of fewer calories
of a buffet meal,
compared to the placebo
control group.